today we're going to finish our brief
overview of 17th century rationalism
and I want to give some attention to a
person in that group
who is very important for the Legacy
that he has given to the church
and I'm thinking of the French
mathematician physicist and theologian
whose name was Blaise Pascal
and Pascal is interested interesting to
us because he combined a passion for
Christian apologetics a concern for the
The Logical aspects of Faith but
had a certain twist to his thinking that
makes him somewhat different from the
other thinkers of the same period and
that is Pascal was a man of profound
passion who
emphasized in many of his writings the
relationship of the heart
to Christian faith and obviously a lot
of that was a direct result of a
personal religious experience he had
that was so intense
that it turned his life upside down and
left him such a changed man
that he was in a sense preoccupied with
his spiritual experience from that day
forward
now he was as I said a theologian of the
Roman Catholic church but strongly
resisted the Jesuit order of that church
and resisted much of classical medieval
theology
and he was involved in a movement in the
17th century that also has great
historical significance a movement
called jansenism
and jansonism was important because it
represented a post-reformation
Revival of the Theology of Saint
Augustine
but from within the Roman Catholic
Church rather than outside of it as was
the case with the Protestant reformers
Luther and Calvin both were very very
much influenced by Saint Augustine in
their theology but their commitment to
Augustine LED them to leave the Roman
Catholic communion whereas Pascal
remained within the Catholic Church
though he became part of this group that
were engaged in the Revival of
augustinianism that sounded almost the
like pure Calvinism which then came
under the criticism of the church and
ultimately was condemned as a heretical
movement by the church but there was
also a strong mystical element that was
found in this particular movement and
that would strike a chord with Pascal's
emphasis on the heart
well the probably the most important
work that comes from Pascal are
what are called the ponce's
which simply means the uh
Reflections or thoughts and they are
sort of a Loosely knit collection of
ideas that he penned during his lifetime
the ponce's weren't published until
after his death
but the two facets for which Pascal is
most known historically or first of all
with respect to his understanding of the
uniqueness of man and he gets again a
slightly different twist
to uh
the understanding of man from the
somewhat cold and Abstract view of the
Middle Ages that simply saw the
uniqueness of man consisting in our
rationality and our ability to make good
choices and that sort of thing
rather Pascal spoke of man as the great
Paradox of creation
and the paradoxical character of man is
found in this that Pascal said that man
at the same time but not in the same
relationship is that creature with the
highest grandeur
and that creature with the worst misery
and so that we as human beings live our
lives in this paradoxical environment of
oscillating between Grandeur on the one
hand and misery on the other
now at what sense does he find man's
Grandeur well here is a point of contact
with the earlier thinking of the church
that is finding in the human species the
advanced ability to think and to reflect
to a degree that presumably no other
creature save for the Angels is capable
of pursuing
that we can contemplate ourselves and
our own existence and our own life
situation
we wonder how much a an aunt who is
industrious and prepares for the future
and so on has the ability to contemplate
his own existence his own destiny his
own origin we talk about the animal
kingdom as including creatures who
operate through some kind of basic uh
response to external stimulations and
and by Instinct I'm not sure what
Instinct really is but it must be a
lower form of Consciousness but in the
case of Pascal he understands that man
is contemplative
by Nature we have been given by our
creator this unique ability to think not
only to respond to what's happening
immediately but to think about tomorrow
and to have memories of yesterday and
not only that but to evaluate the
goodness or the Badness of our life
situation
so man is of the highest Grandeur
because he has this capacity to think of
himself reflectively
and yet at the same time this ability to
think
is what provides the worst kind of
misery for us because not only can we
contemplate our own existence but we
always have the ability to contemplate a
better life
than we presently enjoy
and with that
the realization that we are unable
to accomplish it for ourselves
that is to say the power of the
imagination is such that we can conceive
of life without pain
of life without problems of life without
suffering of life without death but yet
we are powerless
to escape suffering we are powerless to
escape death and so that all of our life
is lived with that cognizant awareness
of the reality of pain the reality of
suffering and the certainty of death we
all go through life
with the Sword of Damocles hanging over
our necks we don't know what tomorrow
will bring we hope
for good news
but we fear the bad news
now again the misery is in being able to
contemplate a utopian existence
a Return to Eden
an experience of paradise and we have
that with the view of heaven but we know
that until we go to heaven we cannot
experience it and so in that sense we
must always live in the context of a
certain frustration a certain misery of
not being able to rid ourselves
completely of all of the potential and
real problems that attend human
existence
but this business of the thought of
Heaven
is something that because of the
profound religious experience that
Pascal had
that it was not simply to his idea the
empty imagination of psychological wish
projection whereby the creature just
projects into the future his idea of
absolute Bliss and happiness because
Pascal being a Christian was convinced
that there is such a place as heaven and
that he was living his life with a view
towards entering into the final rest
that God promises his people now some
people in the academic world in which he
lived were quite skeptical about this
paradicical place that we call Heaven
and and not only were they skeptical but
in many cases they were cynical
and they wanted
reasons to believe in this future state
of happiness
well it's it's at this point that Pascal
delivers a kind of twist that makes him
famous in the history of apologetics
because normally when Christian
apologists seek to give a reason to
believe in the existence of God and to
believe in the existence of heaven and
to forgive a reason for the hope that is
within us they will point to all kinds
of of logically constructed arguments
such as the cosmological arguments and
the ontological argument as we've seen
already with Anselm and the like
but Pascal took a different approach to
this in a sense he was the Groucho Marx
of the 17th century he he was telling
that everybody was playing the game You
Bet Your Life
so that everybody in this world
has to make a decision at some point
as to where they're going to invest
their energy where they're going to
invest their hope and how are they're
going to live their life are they going
to do it by faith in the promises of God
or are they going to restrict their
decisions to responding simply to the
secular perspective to what they can
taste and touch and see and feel and
experience Right Here and Now
and then and the and and the final
analysis
Pascal understood that everybody has
already in their lives that wherever
they are in their lives
made that decision
that you at the present moment are
either living on the basis of a
Christian worldview where you are
believing that God exists and that he
will reward those who search him search
after him and who seek to obey him and
that he will punish those who flee from
him
and if you live your life on that basis
you are living what we call it Ligonier
Coram Deo before the face of God with
the god hypothesis the god concept the
very center of your thinking it's a
theocentric life and world view
whereas other people who may tip their
hat to the theoretical existence of God
live as if there were no God that is
they live out what we've called
practical atheism
and that person who lives like that in a
very existential sense
is betting his or her life
that there is no God
and that he will not be held accountable
for his behavior at the end of his or
her
sojourn on this planet
and so Pascal mused on this business and
came up with what is called now in the
history of theoretical thought Pascal's
wager
and the wager goes something like this
that if a person
bets his or her life
that there is a God
and lives in light of that bet
refrains from
unrestricted evil
seeks to live sacrificially
seeks to forego some of the pleasures
that are offered by
the world
that if that person dies and there is no
God
in the final analysis that person really
hasn't lost anything
because that person has enjoyed a better
life
whereas the person who bets
that there is no God
and lives their life accordingly by a
one lack of moral restraint indulging
their own Pleasures following after
their own lust
living as a self-centered individual
and then that person dies and finds out
that there really is a God
that person's in big trouble that person
is now facing the consequences of the
Eternal Judgment of God
and so in a sense what Pascal is saying
to the agnostic or to the skeptic
that if you don't know if God exists if
you're not sure that he really is there
and he really is the one who will judge
you at the end of your days
in the midst of your uncertainty
the best bet that you can make the
sensible bet that you can make is to
protect your downside minimize your
risks and maximize the upside and the
practical
intelligent thing to do would be to bet
that God is there and is true again if
your bet is wrong and you lose you
haven't lost anything
and if
you bet that he isn't there and he is
you've lost everything
now
a lot of attention has been given to
this particular wager and people have
sought to poke holes in it the first
thing I want to say in defense of Pascal
is as I said earlier the ponce's the
book that was published after his death
of his Reflections were just that they
were isolated Reflections not a fully
developed systematic study of this sort
of thing
and he's thinking on his feet as it were
and thinks about this and said well what
if I'm wrong or what if I'm right and he
does that and some people were saying
well wait a minute
is this a sound argument for the
existence of God well if you look at it
as an argument for the existence of God
in the theoretical sense I think the
answer can only be no it's not a sound
argument for the existence of God
it's more existentially oriented in that
regard even though Pasco lived before
the Advent of existentialism there were
many modern existentialists who look
back to Pascal as one who anticipated
the thinking of a man like kierkegger
guard for example who called human
beings to be passionately engaged in the
subjective uh aspects of human existence
walking by faith living by faith living
on the edge of risk
trusting God in the darkness as it were
and Pascal being the same kind of man of
passion as Kierkegaard would be at a
later time obviously is thinking in
these categories
now some people turn the argument a
little bit modified and will say that
the most satisfying
[Music]
human existence is that existence that
is lived with within the framework of
faith and in God because that faith in
God gives meaning and significance to
human existence
and if you eliminate God from your
consideration and from your hypothesis
and are thinking logically and
consistently
the only conclusion you can come to is
the one that Nietzsche comes to later
namely that you are insignificant that
your life is meaningless and that you
are of All Creatures the most to be
pitied in a sense
he's echoing the thinking of the Apostle
Paul as Paul spells it out in the in the
15th chapter of First Corinthians when
he says if Christ is not raised what are
the implications of that then you're
still in your sins and those who have
died have perished all together and you
might as well eat drink and be merry for
tomorrow you die
but you see Pascal isn't quite ready to
give it that either or because he says
if you eat drink and be merry and
tomorrow you die and God is there you're
in serious trouble
because you've lived the life of
unrestrained hedonism
and you will pay
the Eternal price for that but on the
one hand people are arguing for God by
saying God is the only
only being who can satisfy the deepest
yearnings of the human heart and of the
human soul and so it's a matter of it's
an affair of the heart at this point it
certainly was for Pascal that his heart
was Ablaze he said with the fire that he
had experienced in his personal
encounter with God
and people doubted that he would say try
it you'll like it
step into the arena of faith and you
will find the only way to find
satisfaction and meaning
well in one sense that is an argument
for God if we make the assumption
that life is Meaningful
but the hardcore
nihilis of modern thought would say
that's the ultimate cop-out
and the ultimate cop-out is simply to
flee to God because we can't bear the
thought of life without him
well Pascal was not so naive as to
assume that God exists simply because we
want him to exist
but he's restricting his wager to this
if you don't know
if you're unsure
if you're Afflicted with uncertainty
you still have to make a decision
because you either assume that God is or
you assume that he isn't or let's put it
another way we can live our lives
betting that God exists
or we can choose to walk away from the
table and not place a bet at all
however by not placing a bet at all you
are placing a bet
you're betting that he isn't there
because he understands that with respect
to the person's relationship to almighty
God there is no middle ground
there is no neutrality
you're either for God or you're not for
God and not to be for God is to be
against God that's the point now the
other weakness that I have to point out
is this
where the where the bet I think loses
something
is he says that if you bet that there is
a God and there isn't you haven't lost
anything
Well you certainly haven't lost anything
of Eternal value because there wouldn't
be anything of Eternal value nothing
would matter ultimately if there is no
God
however in terms of the personal
aspirations
and appetites and desires and delights
that you have in this world
to be a Christian
means many times
to deny yourself
what all things being equal you might
desperately desire
it's the idea of eating and drinking and
being merry
for tomorrow you'd die
and if I have nothing
but this life
why should I
be selfless
why should I be sacrificial why should I
be concerned about other people
I will have lost whatever momentary
chance of happiness or pleasure I could
have had had I not been deceived into
believing in a God who doesn't exist
so that argument in terms of You Bet
Your Life was not found to be very
satisfying to people who were facing the
moment by moment options enticements and
allurements of present happiness but the
bottom line is this for Pascal
the wise person lives a life of delayed
gratification
and that the Supreme gratification
remains fellowship and communion with
God